oh wait and now as soon as I start I
have to cuff this cops like the worst
it's been here for so long it's actually
not bad but it sounds horrible
so finally meeting well not in person
but on video it's been a while you only
just join the Facebook group right
you've been more involved on Twitter
have been more involved in the Facebook
group and now we're both on both uh-huh
really okay so I mean I've seen you
quite active on Twitter already why not
so just I find it hard to get convey
ideas in Twitter because it's like it
doesn't like things the same way as
Facebook and I have to keep it within
the allotment of characters so I I find
very rarely I have succinct ideas to
tweet I read so I feel it's easier to
also track things like if Twitter when
you put something out there if people
don't see it right away they don't see
it right like it doesn't mmm-hmm they
just have to forget I think that the
people that I see using Twitter like
seriously as a power tool create kind of
networks of tweets they make stories and
then link to their previous stories and
kind of have their own and of little
knowledge management system on Twitter
so yeah but yeah I mean that's a it's an
interesting topic which is kind of
relevant but I just wanted to say like
I've been looking forward to talking to
you for a while now it's um there is a
mystery that I'm I've been wondering all
these months namely you actually wrote a
comment on one of my videos like a long
time ago and then when I clicked on the
notification it was gone so I was
wondering what to happen whether you
commented and then like you deleted it
again so you were kind of like don't I
deleted it it was probably YouTube that
deleted it if I link to something a lot
of time so saying
get deleted because they see it as spam
what was the comment what did I comment
you were actually reaching out to me to
have a conversation oh and it wasn't my
I made a video last February about you
know back when there was not much
content about game B I remembered
searching for the hashtag game B on
Twitter and it had been used once before
so really early days at least on Twitter
and before the scene is exploded there
and yeah a few months later you you
reached out to me there some about
having a conversation and I saw that and
then I didn't find the comment and I
thought okay maybe she changed her mind
wondering about that since then
interesting I do you remember comment on
video and I think he may have been in it
there were like four people in it it was
a bunch of guys talking about tech in
the game be when I first entered game B
I was like how do I get in on these
conversations and I didn't figure that
out but I did figure out how to start
conversations I know so it's fitting the
conversations in as opposed to try to
figure out how to get into the
conversations so yeah I mean that's
that's the thing right you know in in
the ante rivals were there is no
scarcity of options right you just make
your own and see who joins yeah needs to
completely in that sense it's true but I
do have anything organized it like I
want to create the tech that makes it
easier to find people to have a
conversation with and to get their like
information out of those conversations
into usable format but I have no problem
finding the conversation these days are
amazing so what are you doing in the
game be space what is your what is your
or not like a be space but I pretty much
is identify my public activity with that
space have some friends who I don't know
find it interesting but don't identify
too much with with the space but if I
had to say name my hobby then it kind of
like participate to participate into
game be
and the way I'm approaching this is it's
a multi-layered effort in a sense like
I'm trying to achieve many things at
once that are all interlinked and that
makes me very slow as a participant but
I hope that then you know the layering
of meaning Canavan purifies the the
message and so one way I've been
participating is I've looked for a
couple of peers and we have been having
regular calls like weekly every two
weeks
I still call it informal practice but it
tends to be more just discussion and and
gossiping about the space and trying to
figure out okay what's what's next right
and the thing is it's it's actually
quite complex and I would say the course
still is trying to find coherence within
our little group of three people you
know Wendy right like she is one of them
and so this has been one activity then
the other is I'm a computer scientist so
I'm I've been trying to develop tools
that can help me with the group but then
also for my own kind of thinking sense
making note-taking all of that
my dream is to have one place where I
just write down things and kind of the
structure structure emerges that helps
me communicate better that I can
actually use or that I can I don't know
built filter views that again that then
kind of become their own blog post or
something shareable also and also maybe
that can interface with other people's
tools of sense-making then so this is
kind of my obsession to a degree I mean
I've been thinking about kind of
productivity tools and that kind of
stuff forever and and maybe more
generally systems you know they don't
have to be IT but
if I think about okay how can I increase
my willpower then I try to make my own
little systems they can be physical or
paper-based yeah this is something that
has been going on for years but now I
think for the first time it's something
greater than myself in a way like I want
to link to something that's going on
then there is also linked to that there
is the question of the protocol like
what kind of stack technology stack
should one develop these kinds of things
and so I've been interested in
interested in peer-to-peer technologies
and and interested in the philosophical
reasons why why that kind of technology
is better than you know legacy web and a
kind of stuff although my thinking has
evolved around that I think more than
peer-to-peer it's some kind of like
interoperability that is the core I mean
peer-to-peer affords that but that's not
the only pattern that affords it and
then I'm actually trying to okay another
area that I find interesting is the
whole survey aqui Jordan how'd you know
that the transformational conversations
you know thing I find super fascinating
although I haven't been able to practice
much it's I just veer towards hands-on
implementing things rather than the
transformational conversations even
though even there I have some yeah I
have my piece of the puzzle that I would
bring in if I were to kind of really
join a series circling or whatever you
know experimental group but haven't
haven't managed to do that and now the
most recent project or endeavor since I
joined Facebook I kind of realized that
many people have this angle of okay what
others can be look like or what does can
be have to be it's very theoretical it's
very like far like generations in the
future somehow or and then there is
transition be people that think more
like
how do we kind of keep the world afloat
all this time until it can be emerges
and what I'm interested in actually is
we are already here right there is a
network of people there is maybe it's
not a network maybe it's just a cloud of
individual atoms that are not very
cohesive right and within this network
there are individual projects and little
groups and it's actually it's a
two-degree very underground a lot of
videos that are unlisted you know of
conversations it's quite interesting and
so my question or second I don't see
anything all right my question is what
could we do if we put that in the focus
if we put the network itself in the
focus and think okay what's the
structure of the network how can the
network itself become more of an
organism right and so there is this a
Verve a kiss theory that I'm looking at
about differentiation and integration
and small world networks and like his
theory about relevance realization links
to cognitive science and neuroscience
right and and you can really look at the
structure of these networks and yeah by
analogy what what does our multi like
what does our network have to look like
to become more of something that's more
than the sum of its parts
I think that that would be a summary of
what I'm looking at all right yeah I
think we're interested in similar stuff
I don't even know how to communicate the
piece that I'm playing and I'm kind of
comfortable in that space at the moment
like I'm figuring out how to facilitate
a generative conversation how to use the
idea cafe how to create a platform and
it's more about finding people to video
chat with and finding your group and
being able to actually facilitate that
process as opposed to just leaving
enough to chance and allow that to
happen
working on like a scheduling tool for
here's my
here's all of our within the network
right here's our schedule here are
people on your schedule who want to talk
about the same information that you want
to talk about right they'll make a roll
on you in or and flame within that space
cuz every time I put anything out there
it doesn't land in the same way I think
it's going to I just something on the
gimme space at the end of last week for
creating like a food conference with the
understanding to get to like zero slaves
and three tons of carbon and no one
really Harrison I'll talk to him this
morning about it because he's within the
food space but like I'm not really
interested in the existing solutions I'm
interested in creating them from the
ground up including cataloging the
existing solutions and being able to
know which one's the best and which ones
in your area and which ones could be
start in your area and how do you form a
group around that like how do we
actually make sense together and make
the sense making tools together and that
it's hard it's hard to do those things
but like how do we bring that together
and everyone in the game bSpace seems to
have their own project that they want to
keep hold of right they want other
people to come on board to their project
but like they said I want it they still
want it to be the way they learned about
it before on the same way right like
it's projects and what is the meta
project for that Network right like what
is what can what can we create to
facilitate all of them until the point
we're all kind of willing and able to
let go a little bit more of our projects
or bring them together how do we have an
opinion about that and it's something I
haven't heard much and actually as you
say I see this pattern of I don't know
Joe Nell has her platform for projects
right he lived
Phil Phil created the wiki with
basically one good article which is his
sense making out but then nobody
participates in the wiki or maybe now
something is starting I don't know and
try to check today but there was some
spam issue
you have your project I have my project
and so on and there is his energy of
like please please join my project right
like otherwise nothing happens I like
you know like there is a different way
of operating that I think is more
effective and I've come to call it micro
contributions at my tias basically it
leans a bit on Bonita Roy's idea of an
organisation she has she has like an
acronym for it
something like an organization that
always reach reaches its starting point
something like that every step brings
the organization back to the starting
point right so when you when you say
please join my thing you start something
and then there is a big loop that begins
right like people have to join and so on
and so forth and unless people join and
collaborate and the project comes to a
conclusion all the effort was wasted but
the micro contribution is kind of like
the opposite if you do something that is
kind of done immediately as you as you
share it it's already finished and you
you craft it in a way that it is is
infinitely reusable so that there is no
cooperation needed around it or not I
mean no coordination this is another way
I I frame it like core what we need is
called cooperation without coordination
right and I think that's also what
Jordan Hall means when he talks about
hyper collaboration when you know things
are happening all the time and I don't
even know and at at a certain point
through the kind of the path of meaning
I will meet the right person that has
the answer when I need it you know like
kind of synchronicity in that sense and
and so this is the approach that I've
been trying to follow like on Facebook
because with every little
post that I was putting out there I was
not telling I was not saying hey here is
my project please join me I was just
like okay a little statistic right a
little poll that people can answer and
everyone will be able to draw their own
conclusions from that
Paul the next day I do another poll I
didn't announce that I would be making
like a number of faults and but then I
can link to the previous poll and it's
like okay each micro contribution is
slowly building up to something but I
never announce the project and please
join the project you know um I don't
know it's just a it also reminds me of
this idea of the swarm right like in a
swarm each individual atom just has to
look okay I'm taking care of the guy on
my right and the guy on my left and try
to stay in between and there is again
like this cooperation coordinates or
cooperation without coordination happen
so I don't know this is kind of the
thing that I'm trying to sorry I'm going
to use one last metaphor to describe
this thing and it has again to do with
scarcity versus of these anti rival
Duras resources right and I think that
there are so many ways that because we
are so used to the scarcity mentality we
create artificial scarcity and I think
that putting putting boundaries around
things is is a pattern is that kind of
thing so and and even you know putting a
name naming something or branding
something creating a community that
people should join you know all of these
is kind of creating boundaries around
things that in principle if each
individual thing happening within that
boundary was shared as its own thing
then it would be more powerful so this
is yeah my rant sorry I rant as well
yeah there's because there's a piece
like I want the coordination and yet I
love the magic of the universe that like
when the right person like the right
person does show up with exactly what
you need when exactly at the right point
I also want to be able to have
technology coordinate that right to say
hey I'd like to to have all the micro
contributions actually lead to the macro
right to have it be simple and easy to
contribute you can feel like you
actually did something but have it be
part of the group with a bigger hole
because I can see what you're saying
about having like a boundary around a
Facebook group but also it's hard enough
to to find those to find those groups
with without a boundary I'm sorry with
the boundary taking the boundary way
actually makes it harder right like how
do you find your people how it game be
even have started if there wasn't a game
be Facebook group and a game be Twitter
hashtag you know what I mean like you
can't just find the game be within cloud
I think that these two examples are like
significantly different or fundamentally
different like the Facebook group or the
Twitter hashtag right if you think about
it like the hash tag is something that
it is not that close group anyone can
use it right and if it becomes too crowd
that someone can create a new hashtag
transition D right because I'm more
interested in that and the Facebook
group is has this completely different
dynamic right now and obviously it's how
it has to do with the fact that they're
like the most authoritative people are
there and spend time there and so
everyone in a sense would like to get
the attention of I don't know Jordan
Howell Daniels muscular I see that
dynamic right there is a certain kind of
power play that's happening because of
the nature of the group but probably
they will I do know it has its own place
right yeah I mean right now I see I
think I I joined in a moment of low
sovereignty to be honest you know like I
it was like an impulse it was not that
like thinking it through because I do
have that that's the addictive
relationship to social media in general
like and the fact last year I deleted
Facebook I deleted Twitter I deleted
Instagram I didn't manage to delete
YouTube because I have
so I spent so much so many hours in that
channel but then it has all baby it has
all come back except the Instagram
Facebook and Twitter
yeah I recreate the new accounts to
participate in the game people own
conversation and I still feel two ways
about it in a way you know like I there
was a phase in which I had no public
appearance and I was just enjoying the
happenings of the game be seen from kind
of behind the scenes and that was felt
cool too because we had some you know
underground conversations and they had
impact we saw we saw the impact that
they were having but kind of from behind
the scenes powerful to write in a
different way yeah yeah it's interesting
watching it all come together and not
come together and it's like chaotic but
in this weird or mean way I mean we're
with together tech it was just me and I
have entered the game be space
everyone's like we don't know how we get
to game B I'm like I know how we get to
Gainey be like I'm not gonna pretend I
don't
I can't necessarily communicate it in a
linear way but it's happening and I
don't think it takes generations I think
it takes a handful of us to come
together to create something that
anybody can be part of and then it grows
and grows from there if it's if the
solutions are Omni when and concentrated
not necessarily peer to peer and and on
the stack because those things are just
gonna feed off each other right you you
each have your own project and no one
else wants to join it and yet owning
that right I have my own project and yes
it's the meta project but it's still the
same thing right it's still I want
people to join it and so Bentley joined
he has his own project reason score and
we've been meeting live on YouTube for a
few months now
and now notice seems to be joining as
well and my brother as a this last
weekend it's like yes so we're gonna be
having our Friday we each have our own
project and then the bigger meta project
and then project raisings on Saturday
that our
you can bring your project to it and how
do we get to the how do we create the
system that helps all of them and how do
we create the communication pieces and
how do we create something that isn't
already being done and it's just a fun
space to play in because it is it brings
up a lot of emotion and ego at least in
me I can feel of like this is mine and
it's not mine it's not mine in any way I
don't own Gabey for sure and I don't
even own the thing that's literally
coming through me it's happening in
exactly the right space but having but I
still want more organization like this
idea that everything happens in there
it's like yes and we can organize it so
that when it happens it doesn't need
every piece of it doesn't need to happen
to every person you can have the next if
I know I need legal advice I know where
to go for legal advice if I know I need
financial advice I know where to go for
financial advice and I think that is the
next step we're taking and is fine you
know how to bring people together with
projects and offer them something that
they want to be part of the more meta
project and not making it be ours right
like how do how do how does that happen
okay I have to take a step back because
I find myself reacting with skepticism
and I'm tempted to enter an
argumentative mode but I'm not sure that
that's appropriate order that's what we
want you know wondering because at the
end of the day it's just a feeling so I
would be I think it would be
confabulating arguments and you might
have answers to all those arguments the
feeling would still be there
trying to think what what the right
approach would be here there definitely
is a fear of losing power
there definitely is something like that
there you know like my project I have no
control over it and so the like the
trust that would be needed to kind of
hand over part of the control or I don't
know I don't even know what you know
maybe even just the credit part of the
credit right and this might be linked to
I don't know a tendency of mine kind of
being the lone wolf and and it's not
it's not productive that's for sure
[Music]
to degree though it's an aesthetic as
well if I think about open source
libraries there are kind of two types of
libraries there are these small little
things that do one thing and do it well
it's the UNIX principle and they are
barely updated you know they once
they're there they're done maybe once in
a decade someone finds a bug and it gets
fixed and that's it right so no new
features no nothing it's just there and
it does its thing and that's what we
would call a micro contribution right
it's small it's maximally composable and
it can be owned by one person right like
one person thinks deeply about the
problem finds the one little solution to
that very well specified problem and and
that's it
the solution is there for everyone
forever and then there are these other
things did these big monoliths that
these frameworks
generally it's frameworks that kind of
are there to allow you to do everything
you know
you want to build a website use this
framework you can build any website and
then you have plugins and all this it
takes care of everything
but then the problem is governance
starts becoming a problem right does
this belong to the feature stack or is
it a plug-in that updates and technology
and you know like maybe one quarter of
the feature set now suddenly is being
solved very well by some new thing right
that is somewhere but then now we have
to decide whether all these hours that
we invested and then the technology
becomes tightly coupled and that's a
nightmare right and so it's certainly an
aesthetic thing probably there is a
place for such projects as well even
though I found myself as an engineer
avoiding them more and more in my life I
don't know yeah you probably not
familiar with meteor but that would be
an example to twin country or meteor you
know exactly I mean that I I founded a
start-up built the technology on that
stack and it took me two years to get
out I mean in the end that startup we
for other reasons we closed it it never
went anywhere but I never managed to get
away from that monolith where every
little library was like you were stuck
with the whole thing and so it's kind of
like when I think about meta projects
this is the feeling that comes online of
the thing that then suddenly like my
contribution is part of this bigger
thing and instead if I didn't label it
or like I didn't brand it or I didn't
kind of kind of like connected or couple
it strongly with this meta project it
would be simply this one thing that
maybe it's not even be related it's just
like it has an input it has an output
anyone who needs that thing can use it
and that's it you know the anti
rivalries nests maximize yeah
like the intellectual piece of like
everyone being able to contribute to the
comments and take from the you know like
it's it's how many what antivirus is
game be in the future but how do we get
there when we all want to keep track a
hold of our own baby news and we all
want you know what I mean like we want
to make a living and get our
intellectual property on the way there
right like we want someone else to show
off our ideas when we're and so it's
partly owning that right and how do we
come together keep stay sovereign
individuals keep hold of our projects as
long as we feel we need to keep hold of
our projects and at the same time help
each other right like find the common
pain points and solve marketing together
so I'll finance together solve our
individual lives together so we can
concentrate on our projects to the point
that we feel safe enough letting go of
them but only ever if you feel safe
enough right not with the assumption
that everyone has to just like I'm never
I'm never gonna give up my sovereign
individualism
but I get to choose whether and part of
a group right I get to choose how much
together we've made rules and then I get
to decide if I want to participate or
not or I want to take my sovereign
himself and go somewhere else okay I
mean it's interesting the things that
you mentioned are not necessarily coding
related right it's more like it's more
about everything outside the things that
are around the expertise okay that's
interesting well then I guess I have
another a follow-up question and I
believe I didn't know the answer and I
don't find it so satisfactory but yeah
let let me let let me ask you how much
have you thought about governance
because the way I understand it is very
basic democratic democratic process
right we've four big decisions we vote
and the feeling that I have is that
that's just very very beginning of
thinking about governance and if you
want to have a meta project
does everything democracy like just this
basic democratic principle is not going
to do it yes
so there's so many facets of answers
that yes I've thought a lot about
governance for together tech when it was
more met on my project um before letting
other people touch it
the idea was until we didn't need one
there would be a board of directors who
would be empowered with liquid democracy
so your members and power them and they
get to come to consensus and/or vote if
they come to a standstill with the power
the members have given them right so you
have between 0 and 99 percent of the
vote or 100 percent of the vote I guess
sitting around the boardroom but that's
my version of how it would be now that
we're growing up we're building it from
the bottom out it's not that it's we
don't have an entity yet that needs
governance its sovereign individuals
coming together let's figure out how we
can coordinate a conference let's figure
out how we can what would what would you
need in that meta project to be willing
to come and participate to be willing to
at what point would you be okay giving
up your baby even if you don't ever have
to just like a thought experiment right
like well if I maintain 51% ownership or
if there are a million people involved
and they I don't know what those that
barrier is for people but you get to
maintain yourself in your project but
you can also at what point do we have
enough funding enough numbers I'm not
enough to offer you that you would give
up your project right like that you
don't ever have to it's it's dealing
with that stubborn individual and
sovereign groups and saying yes this is
dealing with people where they are right
if they don't feel comfortable giving it
up and who does right now nobody then
what would make that safe enough if you
have got salary would you feel safe
enough right like what is the level so
maybe I don't understand yet what what
that means what what does it mean to
give up a product because because okay
I'm going to add the context which is
that my projects that I'm contributing
to game be
are basically in the public domain I
don't want anything in return like they
I have already given up yeah these
projects plus I'm building them or and
trying to build build them in this
minimalist way so that you know like
they are they can be maximally reused so
I don't know what more I could give up
the question right so I'm not talking
about that type of project I have those
as well and they just go up into the
world and they're already in that space
but if we build something together which
is what I had envisioned for together
Tech is like we and I'm still envisioned
and I'm still working out how we
actually would do that together the idea
for the food one was we'd get together
for a conference have an idea cafe on
what are you currently doing for food
and what does that mean for your body
the environments and the world and what
could we be doing in groups of ten in a
hundred and a thousand and then if
something came out of there how do we
fund it how do we create it how do we
how do we work through that process
together if we created it in that way we
own it together and then we have to work
through the governance of what happens
when new people come on board is this
owned by humanity or is it owned by the
500 people who started right I hope I'm
gonna be but that's my voice right
that's my vote but I think my brother
has Wiki election as his project that
Lee has reasons scorned as his project
I kind of have idea cafe as my project
although it's also under the together
tech umbrella
yonis has one called kind Act they're
all kind of in their infancy they're not
coated ready to use apps right and so
part of it is you have your own idea how
to make a sense making up and all these
other people are making sense making
apps as well at what point do you let go
of your vision and create something from
the base up you have to decide right
like at what point is my brother gonna
let wiki lection be part of the Commons
that's for him to decide because it's
his so it depends how like these are
things that you're actually putting time
actually putting money into and what
point are you willing to maybe it's
selling it to the comments maybe it's
maintaining ownership and having other
people come on board but they'll get to
decide if they come on board if you
maintain 99
ownership and all of the power no one's
gonna come on more project right so it's
about solving and marketing finance and
people for each individual project how
do we do that together so you don't have
to give up your project but there's a
tool that helps you get those problems
solved okay
please correct me I'm still not 100%
sure I understand it because from what
you say my sense is that I have already
given up my project like it's already
yours it's already you know on github
download it modify it or use it you know
like it looks like it's not about my
project it's about my time like from now
on what am I going to do am I going to
give up my time to do something I feel
may be less meaningful but would be
shared with other stuff is it about that
or is there something more than I can do
with my projects other than open
sourcing them from the start
mm-hmm that's I mean that's part of what
the individual has to decide when
they're creating a project right is it
open source is it not open source is it
community owned do I own it
the shareholders own it but anyone we
don't have them at a project yet the
idea is anyone can bring their matter
but it's just them and their project and
they never have to give up ownership of
anything they can just come and say hey
I need help with marketing and I need
help with finance I need help with
brainstorm E and how to get more members
right that's what raising project
raising is you don't come to it that's a
share of it we're giving you an hour of
our time how do we help you move forward
with your project in your goals in life
and creating the infrastructure to be
able to do that on a platform creating
the infrastructure to be able to
facilitate that process it's and then
the ideas eventually maybe we have
metrics for whether you can be involved
in it right like if you're a completely
game B for-profit hurting the earth you
know game a company we probably don't
want you to be part of it we don't want
to help you get there so what are the
check box be part of this right
what point do we there's a cost and a
benefit to owning something together but
if somebody owns it already they're not
gonna give up ownership unless there's
something in it for them right including
just the feel-good feeling of giving it
to the Commons then great but most of us
the ideas people in game bSpace have
projects right if you're someone who
doesn't have a project and it is looking
where to put your time and expertise
that's gold right like we want those
people to be working on the projects but
everyone has a project and so if it was
more than the other way around where
there was a handful of projects and tons
and tons of people looking to work on
them then we would create the platform
for the tons and tons of people that
want to work on them but it's creating
both of that it's creating as an
individual projects I want one dashboard
to see with all the projects I'm
involved in and where I can go and how I
can be part of a conversation to help
this one and help this one as a project
owner I want to be able to draw in
people and work with them effectively to
move my project forward as a matter
project holder I want to be able to
create project solutions from the ground
up working through a process and kind of
paint on all three of those fronts at
the same time my phone keeps getting
dark okay honey
I've been following you on YouTube like
I check in the videos and so I am more
or less aware of what's happening I
found that interesting that the project
project raising and also their I mean
the rather project of the conversations
I follow them quite find them quite
interesting it's cool that you you are
all willing to share that I like that
mode of participation
I mean I this is something I find
interesting this approach of like okay
everyone has a project that's a problem
because there is overlap between the
project right absolutely
now I think in my head the solution is
still a different one and then then the
new the one she would approach or
perhaps I guess my my input would be
taken in if I were part of it but so my
approach would be a clear separation of
concerns rather than trying to do
something together like oh let's have
this bigger project that like puts these
four together I would say okay wait I'm
doing this and you're doing that there
is overlap how can we differentiate more
so that my project can Indian interface
with your project so this is kind of the
approach that I would follow and I go
towards this this pattern of doing one
thing that does it well what for once
and then it's done you know it could be
a micro protocol it could be okay you
find yourself with this huge meta
project vision maybe I would be able to
solve maybe even from the outside you
know I'm it's a generic I like how to
have a meeting that's successful you
know like a little protocol right and
and that's it right that's my project I
don't need to you know like share it
with anyone because it's it's a
beginning and an end and and then it's
done you know and so and then
additionally there is this you know
there is already so much that's
happening along those lines without any
meta project needed to coordinate that
right there is already so much that is
being added to the Commons especially in
in in in terms of open source software
um so that then the question is okay
like if it's already happening and there
is a phenomenon there it's powerful and
so on like where exactly is there is the
the the umbrella project
right if it's already emerging on its
own yeah best argument for helping each
other with that with a kind of boundary
you know marketing and so on like for me
with open source technology I love open
source technology anything I'm part of I
would love to be open source technology
but it also isn't I'm not a tech person
i discord annoys annoys me a lot like I
can't deal with discord face looks kind
of like the level of my technology that
I can handle I can't code anything I
can't I can't do that and open-source is
accessible and open to people who know
technology I have to pay for my worm
dress right because I don't have these
skills and ability to make it work for
me for the free level and so to be able
to have a tech cooperative that's
dealing with the actual user to say hey
I have this problem I want to be able to
work through it to a solution and have
somebody code that solution is only
available in the tech space like even
this like hacker activities thing that I
just joined I'm like wait do you have to
be a coder to be part of it like this
isn't it Sun accessible to everyone if
we want 7.5 billion people to be
involved eventually writing game be it
has to be accessible to everyone
intellectually and technologically and I
don't find open-source is that's and a
lot of times the open-source projects
aren't pretty and they're not user
friendly and so something that it's an
essence a seed we can grow can be both
user friendly and have an every project
that started has a lot of risk to it it
you don't maybe have risk because you
know how to code yourself but if I don't
know how to code not to pay someone ten
thousand dollars to create a scheduler
and then it doesn't go anywhere because
people don't want to use it
Selvi that to me is a matter problem
it's like getting people together to say
we have a problem how do we create a
solution and then how do we fund it
together okay I find this interesting I
didn't realize that you are not a tech
person you know because I assumed
because you're building attack you
actually are and so it's interesting
because so the curse of knowledge of
someone who belongs to that III has
surely have some blind spots
and so that that's that makes this an
opportunity to see kind of like okay
what's the what what do I take for
granted that yeah people from outside
these don't don't see or don't know yeah
or difficulties that I don't have
because it's my expertise right yeah
that's interesting and at the same time
I feel like I have seen at least a part
of what game B could be in this space in
open source and like there is a baby
that I wouldn't want to be thrown out
with the bathwater you know they didn't
and so I'm wondering whether I'm failing
to translate the pattern because when I
talk about open source to you it just
appears as this kind of ugly and awkward
non professional ecosystem yeah all of
them yes like that is what it clearly
right and it's doesn't that piece of it
to make it better for people who aren't
techy and need the beauty and need the
like efficiency of something like
Facebook and I do think we can have both
okay okay some in a sense money could
play a role in in building that last
mile to to the actual end user yeah okay
so actually yeah that money is its money
part of the picture of the tech
cooperative is the idea like okay let's
build projects that should make money to
the to the people that are part of it
not necessarily the idea is some
technology makes money right very
naturally something like uber that's
owned by the people is gonna naturally
make money other things like Wikipedia
don't naturally make money because we're
not we used to paying for information
having one umbrella that gives you as
the user access to all of these
different technologies where you're
getting a lot of you're paying $10
getting way more than $10 a month of use
right you're getting information you're
getting systems your debt in for $10
right the user gets a lot out of it the
people doing the work also have to get a
lot out of it they need to know that
when they're putting their time and
energy into something it's going to be
at least them not taking on risk and not
be able to feed their family
so having an umbrella that has a funding
model as part of it now we're not there
yet in any way shape or form we're just
meeting for like what kind of matter
project could we create no one's gonna
pay $10 something when they're not
getting anything out of it so it's it's
yes we need a funding source that deals
with funding at the umbrella level
instead of each individual project right
like how do we create $50,000 to create
this well is it worth 50,000 and how can
we bring that down and how can we make
sure it's worth it before we create it
and that's getting people involved
before before I not just like created an
idea in my head and I put 50 thousand
dollars and now I get fifty thousand
dollars out it's finding how to spread
that risk out and how to create a funnel
it's reliable I'm just realizing that
the one of the big risk that you have
that's going to basically be the
compound of all the individual risks
from all these idealistic people with a
project is that in general we tend to
just be enthusiastic about the idea and
just we get started and have no idea
whether there is actually a market for
it I mean we're in general if we are
scratching our own itch right and so we
don't even know if there if the if
anyone would actually use the
application once it's done and even
there there are a lot of development
patterns a gelatinize you're aware of
that and so yeah I mean that's a risk of
course that if your project oriented
that you just make project after project
without ever testing or verifying
whether anyone would actually want to
pay for that the umbrella companies
taking that risk on right like if you as
a person want to want to take you're
like well I'm just gonna put all my time
and energy into creating this project
nobody asked you - you're not getting
any compensation for it right but if
there's a way for us to get your needs
met like if your food shelter clothing
is sold because someone else sold that
with their own app then you have more
freedom to do that so it's not really a
risk because you're not put you don't I
mean you're not putting your retirement
money into it you're just putting your
time into it the ones we create together
with our shared funds or ones we've
already decided we have the threshold
for right so we don't create a food app
with five people we create a food app
with a million people we create a food
up with 10,000 people with everyone
putting ten dollars in or using their
$10 a month more accurately you don't
just get to say hey I put in $100,000 I
get $100,000 though right that's more
figure you know later on what is your if
you wanted to sell your idea to the
collective or you wanted to give your
idea to collective
what is it worth then and that would be
we'd have to decide that together right
just cuz you put in a million dollars
doesn't mean a clue or wallers you might
have put in no money and it's for a
million dollars right like how do we
actually discuss the value of something
that gets put in because the idea is
creating technology together a Netflix
of apps that we all own the other
there's both gonna be apps that we
created together that we do truly own
together and ones that we've licensed
we're never gonna license one if it
costs more to licensing than it does to
recreate it so if you're gonna sell us
your app for a million dollars that we
can make it for a hundred thousand we're
not gonna buy your app for a million
dollars right so it's still has to work
within that like market and within we
can make it ourselves we can recreate
Facebook we can recreate uber and if
it's cooperative basically those ones
don't exist anymore if we're big enough
and that's videos then it's not me it's
like that the wing is big enough
something else I'm wondering have you
take at the Jordan Peterson's
personality test does have to be hmm no
and I can never even remember what my
other personality you know the like INF
TP one I can never remember what I am
and it changes there's two of them that
change back and forth because it's
basically 50/50 but I can hmm number one
I am are you aware of the mother
basically yeah the big five so how
what's your level of openness before if
I may ask me what's the other one it's
open it's not opening closing yes or
it's openness and I actually don't know
how you would call the opposite um I
mean openness is basically yeah you like
we are open to ideas and and
experimentation and you like new things
and you find many things interesting I
do I find many things industry and I
also do not like it when my phone
changes like when it updates and have to
learn something new on it I'm like like
I don't like it but I love having new
ideas and under it like and I'm getting
more into try it now break it before you
even try it like try figure it out as
you go because that agile process of
creating something and testing it out
like that is what is a big issue in the
tech space is like well you create this
hundred thousand five hundred thousand
dollar entity and you have no idea if
it's usable we broke it if people want
it and so no and I don't have ten right
so I've had to figure out how to use
existing technology to do what I know we
could create with technology right like
using stream yard for idea Cafe the
point I can get a hundred people and you
do it on zoom like using how do we run a
conference without the scheduling tool
er right like URI no yeah
work part of these things out before we
ever put money into the platforms and
this is okay I have a claim that and
maybe that more
more things I mean you will be able to
solve more and more problems that way
without having to build things yourself
yeah yeah just because of the trends I
see as a developer you know like how
your software updates maybe sometimes
it's annoying but in principle it's
actually quite cool right your phone is
there you're not doing anything and
every little app is just like improving
over time right on its own without you
asking for it
yeah and that's as an engineer that's
close to the more like to the developer
scene that happens everywhere in my
tooling in the techno in every little
aspect technologies that I use libraries
methodologies I'm just I I go day by day
doing my thing and it just improves you
know it like gradually gradually if you
don't know it maybe you don't notice it
if you don't pay attention but like
every week or two or so there is like a
a new way to do something that makes it
more pleasant more efficient better and
and think about what that means like
every little innovation trickles over
you know through the you know in
principle instantly throughout the world
to the people that can benefit from it
obviously it's not everyone immediately
but the compound effect of that data to
me is gonna be already on its way in a
way you know like this is kind of like
we're already through the antivirus
nests that IT provides every little
thing that can be reused by others
that's already an improvement for
everyone else and so this is also
something I'm afraid can become a blind
spot if if you think about like again if
you put an artificial boundary and you
think that there is a so there is a way
of saying that that is the N I H not
invented here syndrome it's like a
tendency of companies
to want to reinvent the wheel you know
there is something already out there
that works because it's it has not been
invented here you know and then yeah and
we don't like it so yeah
I think these are the usual risks
associated with identity right like you
Kray recreate the thing you belong to it
and then things that are outside our
suspect yes and I definitely come up to
that both in the technology space and
also in my own body right Rob like well
it's on ours it isn't like it's not no
thank you at the same time there's a
realness to that that it goes beyond ego
and emotion that if we don't own it
together we actually can't improve it
and we can't create iterations that are
for the greatest benefit right like we
can tell Facebook what we would like
them to do but if we don't own Facebook
we can't use it to cut our carbon and
get to zero slaves we whereas if we
owned it together we could and so that
does it but you also can't recreate the
wheel all at once and so it's the
financial piece of like how much does it
cost to recreate zoom way too much money
we're not recreating zoom we're gonna be
using other people's video technology
and creating a scheduling tool but
eventually if we have billions of people
and we're giving millions to zoom it
doesn't make sense to give it to zoom it
makes sense to actually recreate it
yourself but not because of ego because
of Finance right cuz you're like oh wait
no this doesn't make sense to keep doing
this
because the money internal yes like
obviously yeah no I completely agree I
think that yeah yeah I was not making a
clear distinction between open-source
and and things that are and I guess
again it's a blind spot was mine because
I have been moving within the
open-source world for the last decade
practically because you know software
running on my laptop is open-source
everything I immediately like it's not
open source i I look for open so
alternatives and and so I've been kind
of living in this world and you know
last last spring my channel I had been
using it or trying to promote coaching
business actually I was I was doing a
coaching course and I wanted to promote
myself for the coach and kind of like
this encounter with game B and his idea
of anti reverse nest made me realize
that I'm not interested in earning money
that that kind of diss diss link between
doing something valuable and earning
money I mean obviously I still have my
day job and and I'm going to keep that
as long as game a exists but I think
that game be the dynamic would be
completely different in the sense that
you probably want to be paid for what
you do and you will get almost
everything for free so that's that's how
I look look at it and so in a sense I
did this completely change my
perspective and I started looking at the
things that I'm already getting for free
obviously I can see it more because I am
close to the source which is the kind of
like the digital realm right we're not
there yet with the physical realm and
and then seeing that abundance but even
even the stuff that is not closed stores
like YouTube you know the opportunity
that we have with you can just broadcast
stuff to millions of people in principle
just like that for free you know I mean
obviously YouTube has its downsides and
once they become too much we will
hopefully have another platform to jump
on um but there is a big there is
already so much that we get for free and
and and then I said okay then I will
also start using that attitude and
provide everything I do for free which
makes it maybe for me I feel it less
necessary to join a cooperative because
I don't have all the problems associated
with holding on to my thing because I
already decided it's all out for
like it's just their creative commons
public domain I don't care it the more
people can use it better and and then
yeah it's it's a bit like language right
if I can use a non non IT example right
do you need to own English to be able to
improve it now you don't need to own it
right it's just distributed protocol and
you can buy by participating in it
you are already improving it so this is
the direction I see
oh yeah it's still going so that's weird
hello and that it kicked me out and said
my internet was bad I have had them at
the end of my stream it won't let me
stop the stream it's happened a handful
of times over a few months and so it'll
just keep broadcasting and so I'm like I
have to get in and stop it anyway so
good old technology
so what we're in the middle of talking
about no I'm just realizing that I'm a
bit heavy
like happy criticizing all this right
now and I mean I like that you
participate and that's the most
important thing right and most people
are a bit passive and and so we should
we should really kind of like have more
awareness among the people who are
actually hands on doing things and
that's a small subset I believe of the
scene and and so yeah in a way even
though I'm bit allergic to code due to
coordination like I said we have to find
a way to kind of like find the synergies
between the things that we do even
though I'm not sure like what the best
way for me right now would be to cope -
you know cooperate because in a sense I
see it as a restriction actually of my
possibility to to be active if I were to
join the cooperative yeah so that's
that's a bit because I mean our garden
area like it doesn't eat like right now
if someone comes and participates in the
project raising right they're not
joining the cooperative like they're not
they're just getting their project ray
they're just worse giving feedback on
what they want feedback on and it's like
there's no point where you know like I
don't know if you guys have common law
in your in your country but like common
law just like oops you live together a
year now it's like you're married and
all the same rules apply there is like
that doesn't happen you're not like
automatically in the coop and we're
gonna you know take your project at the
side it's how can we service each other
right like how can we actually help with
that process and so Bentley and I got
together tech or work you know what does
that look like so we're offering the
project raising two people it'd be great
if we could offer it more than just on
Saturday mornings right so and it wasn't
just us raising people's projects it was
anyone could come and you could get a
panel of financial or marketing whatever
that looks like and so we're just
working through what those things looks
like what do we have to offer each other
for free and then also working through
that ego piece of like well I still want
to hold on to my project so how can we
come together maybe for mastermind
groups around people who have similar
projects like everyone in the together
tech umbrella has basically fence making
projects so what does that look like you
create one from the ground up or not
right how can what my brother does I'm a
collection inform Bentley on reasons for
and how can if one of them comes up with
a solution to marketing and or a
solution to finance or solution to sense
making how can everybody benefit from
that so it is antivirus while still
maintaining your own sovereignty and
like you're not allowed to touch my baby
or like you can come and be a part of it
but like we need to get that messiness
figured out right what does it look like
to be a part of one of those projects
and that will be between them and
whoever is involved in it yeah okay I'm
really starting to see that you're truly
experimenting and looking for patterns
that actually work for in an anti
reverse rate way with the people and
like people bring their own
psychological situation and and you want
to take them where they are at right
yeah absolutely
like oh we are as humans right not like
just like let go of the human and work
perfectly antivirus I work in the same
space as you like I figured out almost a
decade ago
that if you pay me for something it
loses value for me I don't want to be
paid for my time I want to find what I
will do for free and do it and I need my
needs
like I want those things to actually be
somewhere so I want to figure out how do
we get our food and clothing and shelter
how do we create things that are
voluntary systems right not one food
source and everyone's under this
umbrella and now it has it's like how
can tech support you in your food
sovereignty how can it support you in
your housing and community sovereignty
and then how do you also contribute your
piece whether it's micro or macro how do
you contribute it and how do we like get
that into like one thing that is Omni
when energy progress the thing that you
are describing is such a weird inversion
and I don't know how to say that in one
book you know like it's similar to when
people are afraid of losing their jobs
because the economy is is getting better
it's weird because in a sense like the
economy is going to provide you more and
more for less money so the dependency is
towards not needing a job you know so
it's kind of like if you look things one
way or the other but anyway there was
something I wanted to ask you I think
it's the Sun yeah you wanted to organize
with this conference about food and zero
zero slaves and and three tons of co2
about wonder whether one should also add
zero killings you know like if if one
should add animals as a standard there
but there it's it's okay the way I look
at this is I'm trying to approach that
problem like any every way the kind of
bottom-up like my core focuses the sense
making tool
and in my opinion the sense making to
shoot kind of like become so powerful to
help you also deal with that kind of
stuff like a bridge that I see which is
obviously not what it's going to be or
what in the end you know if you fill out
the gap in reality it's going to be
different but the bridge that I see is
imagining a tool where you can start
logging things from everyday life in a
very easy way you know like okay what
you eat what you buy your workouts
everything right if you can start
tracking all those things then that's a
stepping stone towards then the tool
informing you about ok disease maybe you
could with your tool also like describe
your values and then the tool kind of
squares the values with your behavior
and shows you look this decision could
lead towards a lifestyle that is more
according to your value right instead of
buying that food to try to buy that food
and you know that kind of stuff and so
this is my way of inching towards that
thing so I want the tool that I can use
for basically my whole thinking I just
want I don't know the stupidest thing
could be just I want one word file where
I could just write everything and then I
want that word file to become something
super powerful that can kind of
automatically generate tweets blog posts
or chats to communicate with other
people like and bad but then also give
me feedback about my life about how I
like faster and thinking patterns I keep
thinking the same thing and maybe then I
realize so this is kind of like the arc
that I'm following implicitly my life
I'm trying to build the tool that I can
use to think out loud into the tool and
and kind of like track everything about
myself so that then the tool becomes
kind of like in between me and the world
like to put it in a very own respective
way yeah I mean I love that I that's for
a lot of my ideas come from it's like I
need this tool to exist to make
of the world everything is too like I've
cared about my footprint my whole life
without knowing that word like I cared
about the impact it had but no one else
does because it's a lot to care about
like it's a lot if it's not easy to know
what your decisions do and it's not easy
to see a different decision you can make
we're asking people to take on a lot of
guilt and a lot of like useless
knowledge that they can't they're in not
empowered to do anything with and that
was the idea behind the zero slaves and
three tons of carbon was that when I
took the calculators that Vinnie had
suggested I have 33 slaves and like 10
tons of carbon well I live in Canada
I don't fly a lot I have to drive a car
for my disability like how can and I
can't afford an electric car I can't you
know like there's real barriers foods
the one thing we can maybe tackle
together but there's this big space in
between you have to solve it it's the
individual and I can't there's no way I
can get down to three times its
apartment and zero slaves like I can't
make this not have slaves in it I don't
have that power you know I could maybe
figure out my food system but I either
have to get off of technology or you
know work with other people to recreate
it and there is this so much energy
involved in the big them solving it you
know Google and Facebook should figure
out how to like use our information
better that's not what they're designed
to do they're trying to use that for
profit you know our governments say to
pass laws like that be great but they're
not going to and even then there's a lot
of bureaucracy and inefficiency that
comes from that whereas if we can work
together how can we actually get our
food needs met our transportation needs
or he needs all of it with zero slaves
and three tons of carbon you don't start
there you know like make it zero in
three tons and figure out had a bunch of
within there here's where I'm at and how
do i incremental II bring it down how do
I make better choices well you need
information and therefore we need sense
making tools we need data collection and
I need it to be easy I need to like take
a sure of my groceries and it goes just
what you bought or take a picture my
receipt that's as easy as it is and
there's a way to do that there's a way
to do that with
technology to make it easy to contribute
your information and easy to find new
choices that involves working from the
ground up and that's art with the food
conference I wanted to find out what are
you do for food no shame no let you know
like what are you currently doing what
happened you work with ten people what
could happen if you work with 100 people
what could we do with our food system
with million people to like start the
wheels turning you don't need to be a
food expert or a tech expert you just
need to get there but there was crickets
nobody wanted to have a food conference
I was like okay that's why it's more
going in the meta project direction
because that's the thing I posted on
maybe that had the greatest traction was
the project crazy it's like oh now I
want to get involved so it's like okay
let's see they're not energy and figure
out how to get solutions to come from
the group for they're already empowered
how you get people in the conference
that's all I want I want a conference
with people in it so we can work through
how to have a conference that ideas come
out of and then how to track those and
how to improve that system see there is
this thing about reality that everywhere
you look you can zoom in forever you
know like we're thinking about this
project tracing that itself could be the
project you know like how do you make a
project raising cooperative like just
that how do you become the best in the
world that project raised you know and
it's it's so hard to like I mean that's
why I asked you to high up and ask
question because I'm ham I know penis
and for me it's extremely hard to focus
on something but there is an emerging
pattern on the other hand that's why I
need my freedom to kind of like meander
but then if I look at it after months
and months I see okay there is actually
fashion emergencies like there's a
common theme there by the way I wanted
to apologize for the spectrum remark I
don't know where that came from I tend
to consider myself on the spectrum but I
actually honestly have no idea really I
myself in the springtime I got sick guns
like beam like I'm on it I'm on it I'm
like I'm on it like I don't need a
diagnosis I know I'm on it I don't know
I mean I remember hearing you make that
mark and I believe I want that kind of
to relate but in a sense that it's kind
of insensitive to people who I'm mad I
don't I think we are all on the spectrum
the spectrum is the spectrum and like
it's literally a million different
spectrums that autistic people seem to
be on the extreme of in every aspect ya
know people fall in the center on most
of those aspects and so but it's like
millions of different spectrums or at
least it doesn't rooms and so it's
complex and yet it's where I'm at
alright I mean did you read about it
because I really just hearsay I don't
even know the definition of that yeah I
believe all right Noel involved in a lot
of autistic community is and every time
something else is brought up I'm like oh
I have that like there's a anti what is
it it's like not listening to Authority
like you're thority tells you to do
something or gonna do the opposite and
I'm like oh I think everyone's like that
but no everyone's not like that and I'm
like don't tell me to do something do
the opposite just and now I know that's
like part of like my friend who has a
son oh oh yeah that's so so so and so
it's like oh that's why I'm like doctors
telling me to do something I want to do
the opposite and that came from not like
listen Simon nearly died several times
but what would you say in your
experience is your biggest blind spot
according to I don't know what people
might have told you in your life or you
might have seen people not discuss and I
get it I know I don't think I it's one
in particular I think it's just blind
spots in general like there's ways I
think the world works I'm like Oh
everyone's like this cuz I'm like this
and then I find out know everyone like
that and then the opposite where I'm
like I'm the only one it was like this
and then I find out actually everyone's
like that those things are the ones that
come up with often where like when I put
out the food conference like everyone
eats food everyone's gonna love to do
this
nope like it's like part of
communication but it's like thinking
things are gonna go a certain way and
then
and I'm starting to realize it at least
is that because I could see there have
to do with dealing with shame and maybe
it's also because the whole subject I
mean it was brought up by these in high
or I don't even know how to do this
Indian I believe who was kicked out by
the Facebook group I think he brought
the subject of zero slaves yeah he is
definitely the one he brought it up and
I was like okay he did say it nicely and
now actually do I like I like the
approach I mean that was it's funny
because I joined the Facebook group in
the middle of that drama and so I was
seeing the things and it was kind of
okay what's happening here and I
observed people who be they behaved in a
you know building bridges rather than
walls that kind of thing and I'm sure
I'm not the only one who observed those
and so I think that's the pattern behind
the pattern you know to see the people
who actually manage to behave in those
you know sometimes those are the leaders
you know oh are destined to become
leaders category like they're the
interpersonal leaders are the ones who
know how to get people to get along or
like how to lead people in that
direction
okay maybe what they mean is sovereignty
you know like not losing your calm or
you know like joining in on the drama
and that kind of thing yes it's not just
a particular strength it's or like okay
some people have done the work you know
to to kind of steal a key in a
functional way in such a situation I
mean for me my work was mainly about
resisting joining in you know because I
had just done the Facebook group and I
kind of like felt the impulse to and so
for me I'm alright I already consider it
a success but I didn't jump in in
different ways this is a success and I
think that's a big piece of the
interpersonal work is it
so Sara Lee are you like Gandhi right
like can you like how revolves how I'm
not a golf is the word enlightened are
you it's how can you get to the next
level right like not jumping in when
you're used to jumping in it's huge like
I'm like I don't argue as much as I used
to I don't jump in and like need to give
the counterpoint but sometimes I still
do sometimes it's like it's a need and I
really love doing it than other times I
can
oh not about myself and kind of pull
back more like a journal make a group a
much better that's great it's just like
improvement as opposed to who's you know
the top 1% of this I actually want to
learn from people who were horrible at
it
and then got good at it more so than
playing it better yeah yeah do you do
follow John Cervenka stuff yes and no I
started in on the conversations and it's
too much I'm like I'm not watching 15
lectures of this guy go through history
no no thank you
I did I mean it's it's good but
obviously not everyone can do that or
and not everyone has the motivation to
do it for me that's kind of like the
other in my mind it's tech right and
then the the psychotic and like at the
epicenter of the psychotic conversation
is Jordan Holland and John the Ray kids
I mean especially the last conversations
they have this tetra logs is for people
having like a chat all together those
were amazing like really like I had kind
of like a semi psychedelic experience
while listening I watched a few of them
and yes they were amazing okay I was I'm
not sure I would have recommended them
to you because you need a lot of shared
context which if you haven't watch to
see if maybe adult as I want like I
understand like participatory and are
weaned like it's brought up nothing like
the Omega space or I'm like I'm good
enough like I understand
I really enjoyed Kristy lectures but I'm
like I'm not sitting for 50 of these I
don't
it's boy stur something about it doesn't
register in my card
like out like okay so there was
something about participating in the
conversation after watching the lecture
which made it stick much more than the
lecture it so yeah so these are very
powerful like the interviews that he
does with people it's cool because they
ask him pointed questions and then he
brings all the machinery and then you
understand the context were much better
than the long 50 hours and I have to
admit after a while I was just listening
to them in the background while doing
other things and so I didn't yeah you
know like you get an overarching
narrative but then the details I was
trying to do that and it wasn't working
I was like that happiness is background
is I can't pay attention and get
something and I can't have it it's
background and get something so it's I'm
not supposed to get this I mean I have
as well as the autism I have brain
damage from having brain tumors and
having my brain swell afterwards and
something happened in that process where
I'm now a little bit better but I wasn't
able to put in new information and so I
spent my 20s jamming information to my
head like just like I'm gonna learn
everything and save the world and it I
got damaged to the point where I
couldn't and I had to go through a
interpersonal journey of like okay yeah
you might not be able you're no longer
smart now now I'm back to know I have
exactly the knowledge I'm supposed to
have so like I don't necessarily think
olive like learning everything on the
outside and learning every new thinker
and every new scientist is where the
information is because and we're all
just regurgitating the same information
nothing new is coming up and it's like
there's something I care more about what
you think even if you bring in other
people's thoughts then what you'd like
yeah somebody Thanks and I mean you're
doing a great job at participating so
yeah sad story but is that why once you
mentioned that you you basically the
government like you you you don't have
to work to live right now yeah yeah and
other things that we're from the
radiation and basically I don't know
better
he's always in pain it is my disability
and then now sorry you have kids yeah
everyone and so do you
take care of them during the day or
she's at school during the day okay she
was and she's been 18 months old even
though I wasn't working she was in
daycare mm-hmm so basically you can
spend the day focusing on these game B
yeah yeah I have comfort and all I can
do now is have conversations because
every time there's if I get stressed my
nervous system shuts down and so I've
both managed to get very good and not
have to being stressed like with things
that happened it was stress other people
that happen I don't get stressed but it
but also very basic stuff that doesn't
stress other people out stresses me oh
so it's like this weird like going
grocery shopping or driving and stresses
me out so I have to minimize it but like
a friend going through a catastrophe I'm
like oh I can keep my nervous system
pretty pretty calmly and oh I very much
learned that I've experienced exactly
what I'm supposed to experience to do it
I'm here on this planet to do it's not
like I don't I would pick my life every
time like I'm like brain tumors single
parenthood all of it it's exactly how
it's supposed to be for me to have the
time during the day like for two years I
can't do anything all I can do is have a
conversation you can't do anything with
a conversation now I literally like
changing the world of three
conversations and like idea cafe fix our
world Friday and project crazy and
one-off conversations with people like
this is awesome I'm really enjoying it
and I'm getting a lot and if anyone else
got it awesome that's actually quite
interesting side aspect of this game be
seen that like the decisions and the
life circumstances of people who are
actually able to participate in a
significant way you know like everyone
has a bit of a different situation you
know like okay there is this mark Newton
I believe on Twitter is super active and
I think it's because he just finished
his studies and he's looking for a new
job you know like so that that's like a
window where he can like kind of do
something and then there is this journal
with her military story
my my personal thing a situation is I
mean obviously I cannot participate as
much but has to do with the choice to
work only sixty percent and dedicate the
rest of my time now on Parenthood and on
this so this is uh yeah I don't know for
how long I'm going to do it I'm but I'm
happy it's in the house months okay I
was like six a half that's like mine no
six five months it's not like it's a
whole like parenting and disability are
of my university degree for teaching me
things like they're like much higher
like oh and I didn't I mean I paid a lot
but I didn't like they did not charge a
tuition for either of those things they
both cost a lot have you heard children
halls remarks on parenting
they're quite I think it's in one of
those videos that are more underground
less public have you heard them I know
necessarily he seems to be more of like
I don't know his parenting philosophy is
but I imagine more attachment parenting
than actually I think he links it a bit
to to these the forest Landry and these
love is like a choice love is what
enables choice that kind of thing so
like treating your baby from the start
or something that can make and make
choices like I think he made an example
of like okay from the start like trying
to see whether when you want to grab
your baby to see whether it makes kind
of like a gesture towards you and then
and then you know like and if you've
already really needs to kind of like
make make a choice I don't know it's
interesting to do I mean I didn't
there's a few times in my parent team
were like oh who has sovereignty here
I'm like really who is in control here
and I don't know there was this when she
was really little I took pictures
all the time and then she got to the age
where like I started asking her and
there were times where she would say no
and I'm like but it's Christmas I need
pictures it's Christmas right like hey
and then there was a point where she
asked me to stop watching videos and
looking at her when she was a baby
like and I'm like wait who owns those
they're all mine like Facebook flashback
right I'm like she asked me not to look
at photos of her as a little kid I don't
know and I think it's very common to
pick a kid up when just because they're
not doing what you want right and like
moving them somewhere else doing
something and like they get sovereignty
over their own body unless it's you know
inflicted on their safety and sometimes
it is you gotta get to work you got to
do something we gotta get the car sorry
you know we need to do this and it's a
constant struggle and I don't think it
is a struggle if you follow traditional
parenting because it's like one the
parents I'm in control but try to raise
a sovereign individual it's like okay
yeah you gotta say you know what the
biggest struggle is for me parenting is
like with every choice could be like
okay there is some something that is not
going well and you can do something
about it and it's always a question of
so what I'm doing is either going to
traumatize this child or if I don't do
it it actually is going to make the
child get used to the the wrong way of
doing things and okay I didn't I didn't
say that well I think I have to make an
example so baby is crying and I picked
him up my baby is crying do you know in
the night I pick him up another question
is okay if I pick him up does am I going
to make him get used to cry the night so
I pick him up more or is it action and
actual need you know and if I didn't
take him up it would actually be bad for
his psychology you know so and there is
no answer you just have to make a choice
and you don't know what what and for me
as you know like as a programmer where
it's like the
world is clear it's crazy and also you
know like even the scientific approach
just doesn't work you cannot repeat
things right you do it once and and the
second time the first time is already
having an impact on the second time so
you don't know whether it's it's a
reproduction or no and you truly don't
you're not gonna know whether your
parents you miss messed up or not until
your kids well into adulthood right like
the people I know whose kids are really
obedient um they're the least obedient
when their parents aren't around huh
where is my kid will do the crap she
does in front of me and away from me I'm
like which one's better I don't know she
clearly doesn't respect me as an
authority figure
she's totally honest with me like it's
like okay I can see I have this weird
like I'm going through unlearning what
society has taught me on gender on
culture on just all of the BS rules well
trying to teach them to the next
generation it's like I don't know you
have to learn them before you can
unlearn them or do I just let me be you
and I'm kind of going with the let you
be you and that might be broken
it might be like make friends and also
owe yourself you'll find them like it's
and she's good at making friends she's
an extrovert and pretty just feels I
don't have and she's taught me them like
I she taught me when she was about to
she had these intense emotional
outbursts I remember not being allowed
to have emotions as kid as a kid so all
I knew was to allow her to have it that
she would have more capacity within her
to deal with that than I do to teach her
how to do that I just didn't want to
break her in the same way and she went
like kick and scream and be super sad or
super angry and then it would go away
she'd just be like happy bubbly fine it
was like okay I tried and it works it's
like this stopping of emotion is what
keeps it in your body and makes it
Johnson and yet then it was more with
sadness and almost like oh that's what
you do just process it it goes away but
anger kind of sticks around
telogen and like actually emotional
intelligence we had this point where
I've got really
three on her one night and the next day
we were talking about it and I was like
what do you do it you're angry and she's
like I'm never really angry it's always
just sadness underneath hmm thanks
five-year-old guru my 40 amazing so yeah
that's yeah I'm not there yet so I'm
looking forward to those moments because
right now I mean it's already amazing I
mean that's actually interesting talking
about gender roles and stuff i from from
men in my life
adult man all I heard was a children
till one are not that interesting you
know like they're bored like just
passive there and but for me it has been
super interesting like I almost daily I
can notice something new that they learn
he learns and like the all the nuances
and differences and what I don't know
maybe it's because I'm interested in
psychology but I don't know I wonder you
know like I've never seen myself as a
very masculine man so maybe that's I
mean you know it's a complicated topic
but I mean I'm certainly happy that I
can spend time with this with this
little boy and and relate to him in a
way that I don't know my parent my
father didn't first and then was not
able to because my mom divorced him and
so you know like it has been therapeutic
actually to be able to spend time with
him and then see the relationship that I
could have had but didn't and then try
and kind of realize in the absence of
something that he now has the
opportunity to have psychologically in
his life that I had to kind of build and
it's still only partially there like
through therapy I call it kind of like
the benevolent I somehow like an image
of an inner eye that just looks at you
in a better man ambulant way you know
like this kind of unconditional love and
the thing that gives you secure
attachment basically for
made something that I'm only slowly
realizing that I had to build it or like
it was gifted to me through people only
later in life and so and that when I
realized it it made me cry and that's
also something that I rarely do and yeah
it's interesting and and this is also
something that Jordan Hall was talking
about with a guy shanks talk about
having like having secure attachment to
life in a sense like and how that might
be the reason why it's a
multi-generational project because the
people that we need to and that that are
going to be capable of giving rise to
true game be need to kind of have this
secure attachment yeah you know yeah you
know Jacque fresco yeah I think it was
involved in the we created the Venus
Project which is very tied to this
project the one that resource-based
economy basically said my people are
coming out of university are going into
university and they were like what can
we take to help make this thing exist
right like basically uh we want to
create game B what do we need to take in
University to help that make that happen
he's like you're already broken like you
can't do anything cuz you already broke
in and like you might like just do
whatever you want cuz like we have to
raise a generation in this it's like no
I'm not broken my brokenness is my
wholeness that helps to raise the nice
gentle like oh you can't raise a perfect
generation like I'm already screwing up
into all kinds of wonderful ways but
it's not about getting it perfect it's
about improving on your parents and they
improved on their parents and they
improved on their parents and so my goal
isn't to raise a perfect kid it's to
raise one that's better than me it's to
raise LeMat like hug for sovereignty
they mean he has more sense of who she
is and doesn't have to deal with all the
wounds but she'll have some because
that's just letting them and figuring
out that piece of it and so yes there is
different
generation of earrings right now that
has more attachments and has more
sovereignty and that's amazing at the
same time leaving it all up to them
right as like we can't even make it for
them or they're not gonna even have the
capacity to make it because we're
entering all these feedback loops that
like we have to do a lot with our
current ego and and movies right now the
next generation well we're also raising
a generation to hopefully have less
maybe that's kind of a hard thing to do
and there's I mean what what gives hope
is the idea of the virtuous cycles right
but when we are when you're truly able
to build something that's good then it
helps others also participate in a more
wholesome way and any kind of there's
this that upward spiral idea that that's
kind of what gives one hope right ya
know I have a lot of hope like I mean a
lot of what we're creating in together
tech and just my role in the world
everything's chicken-and-egg but
everything is like well this existed we
wouldn't have to create it because it
doesn't exist we have to create it but
that same thing that makes this
beginning process so slow also means
once we get the first egg it grows into
a chicken and then it just bleep laces
eggs and it just you know exponentially
use that metaphor
I remember Matthew / Kowski it's a super
smart guy he had talks with Peterson and
Jordan Hall before it was cool I don't
know right now he's a bit more
underground again but so so he once
talked about it not about game B but
like about this what we want to achieve
like more generic way about like a
Minimum Viable wheel right like if you
have only half of wheel it won't roll
right you need that you need a full
wheel a minimally viable but it needs to
be a full wheel and then and then it can
start turning and then you know I mean I
think he was talking about it in terms
of technology but like you know these
cryptocurrencies but Musti
the metaphor is there right and yeah
it's similar to your egg idea yes and
it's funny because my mind wants it to
be complex technology and yet I cannot
in any way create the complex technology
and so my brain keeps making it easier
and simpler and less technological to
start it off like perfect and I don't
know access to it until I do like it's
like I have to fight with this level
before it gives me the next easier level
like fight with this one and it gets the
next easier one cuz right now it's very
little technology meaning of course it's
technology it's conversations on video
chat but it's also not needing to code
anything and it's like how do we get
people together in small groups and help
them together in bigger groups and how
do we work that out and it's just
starting how you doing it yeah it's I
mean the impact that you're having in
the scene or even just the presence
based on just having conversations with
people I mean it's amazing it's cool and
I I personally because of my background
I have this you know hammer syndrome
where everything looks like a nail
and I've done does make that mistake
repeatedly and now I hope hopefully I do
that in a more and more nuanced way but
it's still there this tendency to try to
solve inter-human problems by a code and
but it's like it looks like actually the
most powerful technologies are those
that amplify the humaneness like video
you know we don't need a special chart
to communicate well we just need a video
that like kind of opens and amplifies
the bandwidth of what's already human
communication yeah that's interesting
reminds another project there has been
there have been projects that are video
chat
right there was chatroulette there's one
that's very similar to chat roulette and
they're always taken over by naked
people like that's like or just trolls
right like you're like let's just roll
through until there's not any good human
on the other
or but it's like they're so close to
being right it's like all you need is
also be like the Facebook feature right
where you have like one account and you
don't get to show up and be an asshole
like you don't it's like people don't
show up - I need a cafe and act like an
asshole
they just don't and there's something
about when you don't have anonymity but
it is on video that gets rid of the
trolls we're still human
there's still gonna be an emotion that
arises and there's still but like OD not
- there was a conversation I was on
about John Byrne baking with the future
thinkers where they're like I kept like
for yelling at people for yelling at
people I'd be there like you're the only
one yelling and it's like oh I'm yelling
at people for yelling at people
gotcha but it was coming up in a
somewhat negative way but I also learned
from that much more than if I had an
experience right and so it was I don't
know
very powerful about actual face-to-face
as close as you can get that I'd be able
to meet notes both one-off groups and
repeated that helps human beings evolve
and just have that is enough and yet not
because I want it to be really not
another one I want all the trends but
still I mean I think that's actually
part of the wisdom of the scene that to
a degree we are aware of well we need to
hop medium you know like we try to
engage in text on Facebook on Twitter
but we are very kind of aware of the
medium and and therefore willing to kind
of switch context and and create a new
context like video where something
different can happen I think that this
is a core a key skill of the scene that
you know maybe it's maybe that's what
the scene is here to bring and then
there will be the next scene that brings
the next thing because I actually leave
it I lived the whole progression really
a bit like the narrative that rebel
wisdom has because they were they
followed George Peterson at the
beginning right and then they moved to
the intellectual dark web in general
and now they're following you know the
sense makers sort at all and and the the
narrative there is that there has been a
step wise improving the quality of
discourse so the form of conversation
rather than the content it's more like
about okay the form is always improving
and and so like you know you have CNN
and blah blah blah where everyone has to
talk in sound bites and obviously that's
not productive okay then you have a
certain type of podcast world like the
Joe Rogan kind of thing where it's kind
of a long-form interview and Jordan Hall
kind of a John Jordan Peterson was able
to surf that wave and and kind of what
he also represents in this space is the
congruity you know like I tell my truth
and I show up as someone who tells the
truth
and then there was this whole discussion
about a we if we want to kind of proceed
as as a society we need to be able to
have difficult conversations we need to
be able to talk about controversial
stuff without people immediately losing
the reputation their jobs their
livelihood right and this was kind of
like the message of the intellectual
dark web right people with different
ideologies but in general against
political correctness because again like
stifling discourse but there was still
the frame of the debate I have an idea
you have an idea and now we fight it out
and in the end you have one or I have
one or you know and the problem there is
that not many minds were changed and I
think the peak there was the Jordan
Peterson versus sam Harris debates where
there you had like the New Atheists
and you had this kind of like Union type
of psychological religious mythological
crowd right you had these two kinds of
people and and these debates were about
is science nested in religion or is
religion nested in science you know like
what's more fundamental
and it was still trained as a debate and
even the speakers found it frustrating
that the the crowd was cheering you know
yes yes you you gave him a good punch
and so on right and that was for me like
the end of an era of the debate era if
you will but I think Jorah Peters from
didn't manage to overcome the kind of
confrontational tone or that kind of
stuff he has in himself it's his
weakness basically right this whole like
oppositional frame and and that's why I
kind of like he started becoming less
relevant and now these other people came
out like Jordan Hall who has a
completely new and different way of
communicating right this rule Omega and
it's more like every perspective has
validity and we try to create parallax
and circling an hour with John Rivera
key there's this new form so this is
kind of like my way of following the
whole thing I don't know how you you
jumped into game being like completely
from the side right like how did you
even know that anything was happening I
came on to the zoom meeting literally
Remzi on Twitter was like Oh have you
heard of game B and there's I was like
no and I was much go live for my first
fixer I rolled Friday so I was preparing
for that I was like oh there's a zoom
call right now and I jumped on and yeah
I jumped in cuz I was like I dunno how
to create a B link but I know how
egotistical that sounds and I also know
that it's not at the same time it's like
I have a path and it's actually a very
simple path it's like cooperation
outcompetes competition the more we get
together and cooperate the more it just
happens
and I had a very rigid way of getting
there and it the rigidity has left the
thing like I'm like nope
having technology we're going together
and that helps us figure things out and
help us make sense and work through
solutions together is powerful it's just
who's gonna create it who's gonna
actually get that out there when I can't
and I can't even communicate the big
idea and
enjoying that like getting in the game
be space and getting the conversations
and doing the project raising it's like
everything I'm doing I'm enjoying it's
fun and so this idea that it has to be
hard to do I don't buy like even guys in
stock it's like you know the world is
suffering and like it's really not once
you get to the point where suffering is
like I've experienced suffering a lot of
suffering and I still experience
suffering and it's always not accepting
what is once you and your like with the
game of life it's fun and it's like
right like you show it can be part of a
conversation and the more I need it to
be a certain way the less fun it is and
the more it's just is what it is it
continues to flow in the right direction
like there's something here that isn't
science and isn't religion that's like
magic that happens but it proves it as
it goes so it's not you need to take
faith in it it's like curiosity and then
it proves itself to you as you go yeah
do usually do some kind of meditation or
something I tried I tried to meditate
daily and I do yoga and righteously
conscious I mean they just look for
things that trigger me and I learn from
them that's a very good practice because
maybe possible easy to do because I
can't do hard like hard got taken away
with my neurological dysfunctions so I
can only next level of easy and it's
funny cuz now it looks like I'm actually
quite brave that I can go online and
just be live all the time but I had to
get there like I had it had safe enough
that I was like okay I can do this I
still have never been like live on my
own Facebook channel like my own
Facebook page and now it doesn't even
feel meses airy it's like yeah I could I
don't I don't care I am Who I am
comfortable with who I am because you
have like your real life contacts I
guess I mean this is my real life like
this is what I kind of just exist online
and then in community like that's it cuz
I live in my house and they have
connection through the internet and then
I have my real life eat with them
community that I see
but I don't do I don't really go out
much beyond that so that's finally do
you know what with it I was wondering
why you would feel more you know
embarrassed about showing yourself on
Facebook than on YouTube for example I
don't know I don't know I'm sorry about
it being my friends and family
ya know which means I'm about I have to
go pick up my kid from at school
so it's been great chatting with you but
I will have to end it
notice all right all right thanks dad
I'm just gonna end up